today is the day that I say noticeable
like y'all are not going to dictate what
our lives are supposed to be like you're
not in charge anymore
we're here and as long as we have to pay
taxes you don't have to listen to what
the do we have to say we have to
to say
[Music]
hello I'm Chris Lewis and today we're
going to discuss Marsha P Johnson so the
story begins in the middle of New York
City in the village on Christopher
Street and back then you know New York
had a growing LGBT population so
basically the non-straight population
had a bunch of bars and stuff in
Greenwich Village and so you know all
the queer kids would go down to the
village and be like we're here to be
ourselves but these people didn't have a
sense of community like this was a point
in time where you came out as being
trans and you were just kicked out of
the house like and nobody gave about you
and that was kind of what happened to
Marsha like she was a queer person
growing up in Jersey ok so she would get
on the train in Jersey dressed as
Malcolm which was her birth name and
then on the way over from Jersey to New
York transformants Marsha you know beer
cans and pop cans for rollers it's just
like I'm Marsha Pete Johnson it if
you don't like it you've got a handout
like Here I am though what you don't do
[Music]
you know the best life in the world
so the 1960s is a very tumultuous time
for the United States of America because
every minority group imaginable is tired
of status quo so there was a group of
opposites in New York City called the
public moral squad which is ridiculous
because when the morals my part of this
goddamn city like the city is trash and
the public Marasco I took their orders
directly from the mayor the mayor was
like I want you to shut down the gay
bars I'm sick of them are to need some
people's asses it's time to be over
[Music]
so the nice thumb while June 18th or
28th June 21 of the eights so that night
Charles Smythe as Seymour pine they
walked into the Stonewall Inn they said
we have it fins on the
arrests since you gay ass down and wait
for us to verify it your mother and I do
your mother and genitals sorry tree and
the trans goes was like oh no we
asked for this and some people were like
freaking out and trying to like go for
the exits but the police have barricaded
the whole thing and Marcia says you know
what today is not the mother and day
today is the day that I say noticable
like y'all are not going to continue to
run us to dictate what our life should
be late to just addition to dictate what
our lives are supposed to be like you're
not in charge anymore we're here and as
long as we have to pay taxes you don't
have to listen to what the that we have
to chase we have to to shake to say so
Margie be justice stood the up and she
picked up a shot glass civil rights gia
had enough that day so
during the Stonewall riots at first like
all these members of the gay community
started gathering outside Marcia she
said like oh my god there's so many of
us there's five hundred of the lids of
us by the time back up shorter the
Christmas is way too late some of
the writers to rock
others found bricks by any means
necessary so the people at stonewall
that and I realized there's a community
of us it's not just 20 of us on
Wednesday night when it's half-hour
there's a whole group of us who are here
in this gation and you're not going to
erase this from the mother conversation
number so margin says ultimately human
dispensers ultimately people with that
night and then the next one constitute
the Stonewall Riots and that is what got
the whole gay rights movement in America
started off that gives me chills it's
the shot glass heard around the world a
few weeks later Marsha and her friend
Sylvia formed the street transvestite
right reaction evolution which is not
words but we would use to get today
obviously it would be it more like
straight trans vender transgender I mean
I'm not transmitted I guess basically
Marsha and Sylvia were out there in the
systems I'm just trying to get these
trans kids a place to live
she really was a badass yeah and so
brave like I would not have been that
brave in the 60s and 70s I mean was bad
enough being black right but adding a
queer identity and then a queer gender
identity to it was a lot it was a lot
and she still faced it but truly black
people deserve to be on all black people
in a second you're weird who needs to
get off the goddamn coin they're not
some paper money because this yeah bad
am
hello my name's Alison wrench today
we're gonna be talking about Amy Windsor
and the end of DOMA the Defense of
Marriage Act yes come on I could puke
tonight let's do it yeah let's just get
it out of us so the year is 1950 the
place is the United States of a at this
point in history it's not even legal to
dance closely to a person of the same
sex
so Edie Windsor was a young lesbian
she's like oh I gotta keep my personal
life private cuz this is the past and
the past is closed-minded so then
Edie is in Greenwich Village and she
notices a beautiful leggy brunette she
is hey are you can I dance with you the
woman goes hello my name is Thea Spyer
and yes that's a great name you've got
Edie Windsor and Thea Spyer to like cool
lesbian names yeah you know and then
Edie goes is your dance card full which
is an old-timey way of being like you
single and then she goes it is now
meaning I'm ready they have poles
in them yes balls big girls so
then they date and they fall in love but
then on June 28th 1969 she encounters
the Stonewall riots where gay people
were being out-and-proud about who they
were amid this police raid at this
Stonewall Inn so she goes home and she's
like Thea there's the big riot at
Stonewall about gay rights maybe this is
the moment that we should come out and
and and tell the world who we really are
so she's like I don't know that's really
risky maybe not so Edie and Thea are
like you know well we're not
revolutionaries we're just two ladies
in love and like to dance and we're
gonna be private about it and they do
that for the next 30 years that's a long
time and the thing that they really find
it over was dancing in any situation
their bodies Chloe's connect through
dance and it's about 2007 out in the--
was no wheelchair with MS feels like I
want to get married by this time Canada
had made gay marriage legal so Thea and
Edie go to Toronto and then get married
in four to six buddies they exchanged
rings and Edie and Thea are like whoa
this feels different to truly be married
like there's a tangible difference this
is not that's very sweet to be
like to float the Lord yeah those
laws so in 2009 Thea dies and eating is
there in the hospital and she's thinking
in like I had a good life we had a
beautiful love what more could I ask for
and then not good US government says hey
so your friend iya left you a bunch of
property money assets and we don't
recognize that cuz you're too 80s it's
not like you were married so we're gonna
tax you on the order of half a million
dollars a needy goes you know we
were married and this is discrimination
I'm gonna call a bunch of lawyers I'm
gonna call a bunch of gay rights
activist um so then she says excuse me I
was in a relationship with this one for
forever we got married in Toronto this
is legit they're not recognizing their
marriage so they're trying to tax the
of me and that lawyers and actives
are like yeah that's DOMA you know since
1996 this law was enacted it says on a
federal level a marriage is between a
man and a woman and it's just
undefeatable undefeatable in you can't
do it but then Edie calls Roberta
Robbie
is her name Roberta Robby Kaplan her fun
name is Robby her name is Roberta Kaplan
and this woman goes you know what I'll
take you on you are what marriage is
about you two were married for decades
through sickness and in health your
sweet old woman you're the perfect
example of what gay marriage can be so
Roberta and Edie mm-hmm sue the federal
government and it goes all the way to
the Supreme Court and Edie goes before
them and says if my love isn't real no
love is real we were together
for so long our love deserves to be
recognized so on June 26 2013
Edie and her supporters gather around a
computer pops up on the screen DOMA is
unconstitutional five to four and
everyone's our one cheer too hard
so she goes back to Stonewall in
Greenwich Village and crowds were gather
and they went Edie Edie Edie and Edie
thought to herself Wow
years ago when I walked past here during
the Stonewall Riots me and Thea thought
for now revolutionaries but here we are
years later and we are the
revolutionaries were the face of what
gay marriage Kingi and eating dances one
last dance in the name of the love of
her life
[Music]
Sevilla TPM and Edie Annie wow that's
amazing
thanks to this one brave woman and her
belief in the Equality of her love gay
marriage became legal do you think in in
in memory of them that you and I should
dance we should dance so close well can
I give you a good pack what do
[Music]